A Guide to the Papers of Lewis Preston Collins, ca. 1862, 1918-1952
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Lewis Preston Collins ca. 1862, 1918-1952
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
10615, -a
This collection consists of ca. 8,370 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The main portion of the Lewis Preston Collins, II Collection, accession #10615, was made a gift to the Library by Lewis Preston Collins, III, of Marion on October 17, 1984. The scrapbook of photographs, accession #10615-a, was lent to the Library by Mr. Collins for the purpose of making copies to be placed with the main collection.
Biographical/Historical Information
1896: Lewis Preston Collins, II, born on December 25, in Lynchburg to Lewis Preston and Ella Bolling (Moorman) Collins.
1918: Served as a sergeant in World War I.
1920: Received B.A. degree from Washington and Lee University.
1921: Received law degree from Yale University; admitted to the Virginia State Bar.
1921-1952: Practiced law in Marion, Virginia.
1926: Married Pauline Staley on January 2.
[1928] Dec 17: Son, Lewis Preston Collins, III, born.
1936-1946: Member of the Virginia Legislature.
1946-1952: Lieutenant Governor of Virginia, under governors William Munford Tuck and John Stewart Battle.
1950-1952: Director and President of Marion National Bank.
1952: Died of a heart attack on September 20 in Wytheville, aged fifty-six.
Scope and Content
This collection of ca. 8,370 items (22 Hollinger boxes and eight sound recordings (ca. 7.5 linear shelf feet), ca. 1862, 1918-1952, consists of correspondence, papers, printed material, photographs, and sound recordings, chiefly pertaining to Lewis Preston Collins, a prominent citizen of Marion, Virginia, member of the Virginia Legislature, and Lieutenant Governor of Virginia, as well as to his family and personal life. In addition, there is material concerning his brother, Harold Moorman Collins, U.S. Consul in Tampico, Mexico.
Collins was involved in civic activities in and around Smyth County, working with many projects, such as the Marion-Chilhowie airport, the Civil Aeronautics Administration Intermediate Field at Chilhowie, the Wytheville Diagnostic Center, a Marion elementary school proposal, and an apartment project in the county, as well as assisting Marion in acquiring appropriations from the Department of Highways, regarding obtaining the best possible rural route delivery system, and other activities.
As a member of the House of Representatives in the Virginia General Assembly, Collins represented the Smyth County area with concern for its growth and development. Correspondence with constituents and other legislators show that citizens approached Collins for assistance and guidance in local matters. He was also active in Democratic party conventions, including the 1984 State Democratic Convention where he delivered the keynote address and the 1952 Democratic National Convention in Chicago, and in campaign, and Saxon W. Holt's campaign for lieutenant governor in 1937. In addition, he was elected as the permanent chairman for the Young Democratic Clubs.
During his lieutenant governorship, Collins was a member of the Senate Appropriations Committee, and collected much material from its budget hearings, such as exhibits, estimates, reports, and letters. As lieutenant governor he maintained contact with constituents, often addressing various organizations or attending dedications. Excerpts from his speeches are included.
Topics of interest include family news, the construction of Collins' house in Marion, the Kiwanis Club, the Marion National Bank, management of the Moorman Farm, the divorce of Harold Moorman and Mary (Proctor) Collins, Smyth County civic and political concerns, Southwestern State Hospital, Democratic party campaigns, conventions, and platforms, state appropriations, Booker T. Washington Industrial Training Center, the Medical College of Virginia, Virginia Polytechnic Institute, and the University of Virginia.
Items of interest include an Exemption Notice, March 14, 1862, for James B. Collins (Legal Papers of the Collins Family); a letter, November 4, 1918, from Collins in France describing the last days of the Meuse Argonne offensive; a letter, April 1, 1942, from Collins to President Franklin Delano Roosevelt offering his services in a war emergency (Military Service); a plat of Lot #3 of the H.L. Moorman property surveyed in 1934 (Moorman Farm); Harold Moorman Collins' Patent for a drink mixer; "Memoir and Analysis of Virginia's Participation in the Chicago National Democratic Convention" by Collins (Democratic National Convention, Chicago, Illinois, 1952); photographs from an album regarding Collins' inauguration as lieutenant governor; and recordings of speeches by Collins and tributes to him.
Collins corresponded with many prominent persons, particularly Virginians. Among the more important correspondents are Virginia governors James Lindsay Almond, Jr., John Stewart Battle, Harry Flood Byrd, Sr., Colgate Whitehead Darden, Jr., Albertis Sydney Harrison, Jr., George Campbell Peery, John Garland Pollard, James Hubert Price, Thomas Bahnson Stanley, and William Munford Tuck. Lewis also corresponded with many of the members of the Virginia Assembly during his political career. Specific correspondents, including family members, are listed in the contents list.
Organization
The material in this collection arrived at the Library in twenty-two boxes of varying sizes, including eight letter boxes. Its alphabetical arrangement has been maintained and most folder headings have been retained, being modified only where necessary. Other folders have been interfiled with similar material.
This collection has been arranged into six series: I. Correspondence; II. Personal Papers with two subseries, 'Lewis Preston Collins' and 'Harold Moorman Collins'; III. Political Papers; IV. Legislative Papers; V. Photographs; and, VI. Non-Print Media Material. Items are arranged chronologically.
The papers and other material from Collins' legal practice have been transferred to the University of Virginia Law Library (MSS 85-6) where they will be made available to researchers.
Contents List
- Series I. Correspondence
  - Correspondence 1918, 1925-1943 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence: A-Z 1946, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Correspondence: A-B 1947-1949, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Correspondence: C-R 1947-1949, 15 folders (Box 2)
  - Correspondence: S-Z 1947-1949, 4 folders (Box 3)
  - Correspondence: A-Z 1948 Jan-Mar, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Correspondence: A-Z 1950 Jan, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Correspondence: A-Z 1950 Feb, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Correspondence: A-Z 1950 Mar (Box 4)
  - Correspondence: A-C 1950-1952, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Correspondence: D-O 1950-1952, 12 folders (Box 5)
  - Correspondence: P-Z 1950-1952, 6 folders (Box 6)
- Series II. Personal
  - Lewis Preston Collins
    - Abbott, Proctor, and Paine 1938-1941 (Box 6)
    - Accounts (Payments) 1926-1948 (Box 6)
    - Appalachian Electric Power Company 1933-1935 (Box 6)
    - B.F. Buchanan Memorial Highway 1933-1937 (Box 6)
    - Biggs Antique Company 1933 (Box 6)
    - Branch, Cabell, and Company 1938-1949 (Box 7)
    - Central Antique Shop 1933 (Box 7)
    - Collins Family Genealogy 1939 (Box 7)
    - Defense Speakers Bureau 1943 (Box 7)
    - Estate of John S. Collins 1934-1941 (Box 7)
    - E. Asher Ford 1934-1935 (Box 7)
    - T. McCall Frazier 1934-1937 (Box 7)
    - Dr. Leslie N. Gay re Pauline Collins 1937-1938 (Box 7)
    - House building - Collins Property-Marion 1930-1931 (Box 8)
    - Infantile Paralysis Campaign 1939 (Box 8)
    - Inter-Mountain Telephone Company 1933-1935 (Box 8)
    - Jefferson Standard Life Insurance Co. 1933-1941 (Box 8)
    - Kiwanis Club 1933-1942 (Box 8)
    - Kiwanis Club Committees 1944-1947 (Box 8)
    - Kiwanis Club National Service and Public Affairs 1942-1949 (Box 8)
    - Kiwanis Country Store 1934 (Box 8)
    - Legal Papers of the Collins Family 1862, 1925-1933 (Box 8)
    - Livingston and Company 1934-1935 (Box 8)
    - Lee Long 1933-1936 (Box 8)
    - J. William McCallum 1933-1934 (Box 8)
    - Marion College Annual Reports 1950 (Box 8)
    - Marion High School: Resolution to Reelect W. L. Allen as Principal 1936 (Box 8)
    - Marion Library 1935 (Box 8)
    - Marion National Bank 1938-1941 (Box 8)
    - Military Service 1942 (Box 9)
    - Lindsay L. Moore 1934 (Box 9)
    - Moorman Farm 1936-1938 (Box 9)
    - National Recovery Administration Compliance Board 1933 (Box 9)
    - Charles A. Osborne re Chapter 231 of the Acts of Assembly 1936 (Box 9)
    - Samuel T. Rhoades & Son 1933-1934, 1942 (Box 9)
    - Richardson-Wayland Electrical Corp 1934-1935 (Box 9)
    - Love B. Rouse 1935 (Box 9)
    - Rural Route #1 of Chilhowie 1935 (Box 9)
    - The Salvation Army 1944 (Box 9)
    - Peter Saunders 1933-1938 (Box 9)
    - Sugar Grove Post Office 1935 (Box 9)
    - United States Army Ambulance Service Association 1933 (Box 9)
    - Virginia Academy of Science 1941-1942 (Box 9)
    - Virginia Lincoln Corporation Flag Raising Ceremony 1943 (Box 9)
    - Virginia Military Institute 1937 (Box 9)
    - Washington and Lee Alumni 1934-1942 (Box 9)
    - Washington Baseball Club 1933 (Box 9)
  - Harold Moorman Collins
    - Accounts 1936-1942 (Box 9)
    - Condolences for death of Harold M. Collins 1942 (Box 9)
    - Correspondence of Harold Moorman Collins 1923, 1934-1940 (Box 10)
    - Correspondence of Harold Moorman Collins 1941-1942, n.d. (Box 10)
    - Miscellaneous 1936-1942 (Box 10)
    - Patent for Drink Mixer 1935-1942 (Box 10)
    - Treasury Department, Internal Revenue Service 1938-1942 (Box 10)
- Series III. Political
  - The American Assembly 1951 (Box 11)
  - Harvey B. Apperson 1933-1938 (Box 11)
  - Harry Flood Byrd, Sr. 1934-1935 (Box 11)
  - Campaign for Election to the House of Delegates 1935 (Box 11)
  - Campaign for Re-election to the House of Delegates 1939 & 1941, 2 folders (Box 11)
  - Campaigns General 1932-1942 (Box 11)
  - C.S. Carter 1935-1943 (Box 11)
  - Everett Randolph Combs 1934-1943 (Box 11)
  - Correspondence re the Campaigns 1932, 1937 (Box 11)
  - Colgate Darden Campaign for Governor 1941, n.d. (Box 11)
  - Democratic National Convention, Chicago, Illinois 1952 (Box 12)
  - Democratic Organization for the State of Virginia 1950 (Box 12)
  - Democratic State Central Committee: Campaign of 1940 1936-1941 (Box 12)
  - Horace H. Edwards 1937-1943 (Box 12)
  - Saxon Holt Campaign for Lieutenant Governor 1937, n.d. (Box 12)
  - Hungry Mother Park: Right of Way for John S. Airheart 1938 (Box 12)
  - Invitations and Engagements 1937-1951, 3 folders (Box 12)
  - Invitations and Engagements 1937-1951, 6 folders (Box 13)
  - Keynote Address of Lewis Preston Collins delivered at the State Democratic Convention 1944 (Box 14)
  - Letters of Congratulations for the Election 1937 (Box 14)
  - Mail Votes 1931-1941, 3 folders (Box 14)
  - Precinct Lists 1934-1941, 3 folders (Box 14)
  - Printed Miscellaneous 1929, 1949, 1951 (Box 15)
  - Printed re the Campaign 1937, n.d. (Box 15)
  - Speeches by Lewis Preston Collins 1947-1951 (Box 15)
  - William Munford Tuck 1936-1949 (Box 15)
  - Washington Memorial Monument Dedication 1950 (Box 15)
  - J. Frank Wysor 1936-1938 (Box 15)
  - Young Democratic Clubs 1936-1940 (Box 15)
- Series IV. Legislative
  - Budget Hearings 1947-1951, 6 folders (Box 16)
  - Budget Hearings 1951, 4 folders (Box 17)
  - Budget Hearings 1951 (Box 18)
  - Commission Appointments 1950-1952 (Box 18)
  - Commission on Reorganization of State Government 1947 (Box 18)
  - Commission to Study Foundation Program in Education in Virginia 1950-1951 (Box 18)
  - Constituent Letters 1937-1938 (Box 18)
  - Constituent Letters 1938 (Box 18)
  - Constituent Letters 1942, 2 folders (Box 19)
  - Correspondence with Senators 1952 (Box 19)
  - Burt Lincoln Dickinson 1933-1937 (Box 19)
  - District Attorneyship 1932-1934, 2 folders (Box 19)
  - Endorsements for Legislative Positions 1937 (Box 19)
  - John W. Flannagan, Jr. 1933-1943 (Box 19)
  - J. Tyler Frazier, Jr. 1933-1937 (Box 19)
  - Game and Inland Fisheries Commission 1936-1941 (Box 19)
  - Gas Rationing 1943 (Box 19)
  - Judgeships of 21st Judicial Circuit 1937 (Box 19)
  - Legislative Bulletin 1940 (Box 19)
  - Legislative Correspondence 1937-1939, 3 folders (Box 20)
  - Legislative Correspondence 1940-1943 (Box 20)
  - Legislative Correspondence 1950-1952, n.d. (Box 20)
  - Legislative Miscellaneous 1936-1951, n.d. (Box 20)
  - Lieutenant Governor 1950-1951, n.d. (Box 21)
  - Lieutenant Governor 1950-1951 (Box 21)
  - Lieutenant Governor: Commission Appts. 1950 (Box 21)
  - George Alvin Massenburg 1936-1938 (Box 21)
  - Benjamin Muse 1936 (Box 21)
  - George Campbell Peery 1933-1936 (Box 21)
  - John Garland Pollard 1933-1934 (Box 21)
  - Proposed Legislation 1941-1942, 2 folders (Box 21)
  - Reports to the Governor 1951 (Box 22)
  - Resolution Commending John S. Battle, William M. Tuck, & Harry F. Byrd, Sr. 1952 (Box 22)
  - Sales and Use Tax 1944 (Box 22)
  - Special Session of the General Assembly 1952 (Box 22)
  - Southwestern State Hospital Investigation 1936-1937 (Box 22)
  - Tuck's Bill to Amend Chapter 13 of the Code of Virginia 1948 (Box 22)
  - Virginia State Bar Association 1938-1949 (Box 22)
  - Virginia State Library Building 1938-1940 (Box 22)
  - John Jordan Wicker, Jr. 1933 (Box 22)
  - Williamsburg Sessions of the General Assembly 1950-1952 (Box 22)
  - George A. Wright 1933-1934 (Box 22)
- Series V. Photographs
  - Inauguration of Lieutenant Governor Lewis Preston Collins 1950 (Box 22)
- VI. Non-Print Material and Audio Recordings
  - Campaign speech by Lewis Preston Collins, Democratic Candidate for Lieutenant Governor [1946], T 827. Cassettes (2) 15 minutes (Box 22)
  - Lt. Gov. Lewis Preston Collins: comments with Walter R. Bishop, WRVA Radio, Richmond 1949 Aug 2, P 608 12-inch phonodisk 78 rpm (Box 22)
  - Lewis Preston Collins: speech 1949 Sep 14, P 609 12-inch phonodisk 78 rpm (Box 22)
  - "Legislative Forum" program by George Passage: Nominations of Lt. Gov. Lewis Preston Collins as Valued Senate Leader recorded by WRVA Radio, Richmond 1952 Mar 4, P 610 12-inch phonodisk 78 rpm (Box 22)
  - Tributes to Lewis Preston Collins: 1) VA Gov. John Stewart Battle; IL Gov. Adlai Stevenson 2) George Passage (WRVA) 1952 Sep 20, P 611 recorded by WRVA Radio, Richmond P 611 10-inch phonodisk 78 rpm (Box 22)
  - Tributes to Lewis Preston Collins: 1) Lt. Gov. A.E.S. Stephens 2) Gov. John Stewart Battle 1952 Dec 2, P. 612 recorded by WRVA Radio, Richmond 12-inch phonodisk 78 rpm (Box 22)
  - Lt. Gov. Lewis Preston Collins: speech dedicating Bluefield, VA Municipal Building recorded by Preston Recording Corporation, Paramus, NJ n.d., P 613 a, b (Box 22)